## Curriculum Vitae

# Álvaro Fernandes de Abreu Justen

(also known as Turicas) March 2, 2016

The latest version of this file is available at: turicas.info/curriculum

#### Introduction



Álvaro Justen is a free/*libre* software user, collaborator and activist since 2004; goes to many conferences as speaker, attendee or even organizer; gives programming and electronics courses and develop software using mainly the Python programming language.

Today he is a digital nomad: travels through Brazil (and other countries) disseminating knowledge through talks and courses (specially about Python, Arduino, free software and open data) while works (remotely) for Onyo (a Brazilian startup) and as an expert at HackHands. Loves coffee, to cook, to travel and to ride a bike.

### Contact & Social Media

E-mail & Google Hangouts: alvarojusten@gmail.com

Mobile, Signal, Telegram & WhatsApp: +55 21 9 9898-0141

Skype, GitHub, Twitter, Instagram & SlideShare: turicas

LinkedIn & Facebook: alvarojusten

Blog: turicas.info

### Professional Experience

- ♦ **HackHands**: works as an expert into the platform, helping programmers to solve their problems quickly, in real time since February 2015.
- ♦ **Onyo**: works as senior backend developer, using Python, Django and other cool technologies to serve thousands of mobile users since September 2014.
- ♦ Curso de Arduino: works as a teacher, giving classes about robotics, combining concepts of electronics and programming, using the Arduino platform and others since January 2011.
- ⋄ Fundação Getúlio Vargas Escola de Matemática Aplicada: worked as principal software developer (Python), systems administrator and was maintainer of the PyPLN project (distributed natural language processing – Portuguese Language) — from November 2011 to September 2014.
- ◇ Intelie: worked as Python developer, systems administrator and was responsible for installations, migrations and operations of the company's datacenter monitoring software into some huge customers such as Globo.com and iG from January 2010 to May 2011.
- ♦ **Peta5**: was co-founder of this startup which was focused on products to the Brazilian digital TV (SBTVD) market; worked as Scrum Master, Python developer (mainly using web2py) and systems administrator from June 2008 to January 2010.
- ♦ Meta Consultoria (junior company Engeneering School, Fluminense Federal University): was selected as trainee and made the whole training course (decided on not joinning the company) 2008.
- ♦ Freelancer: worked as Web developer using HTML, CSS, JavaScript, PHP and MySQL from 2003 to 2008.

### Skills

- ♦ Natural Languages:
  - $\rightarrow$  Portuguese: native, fluent.
  - $\rightarrow$  English: good reading, writing and talking.
  - → Spanish: good reading, intermediate writing and talking.
- ♦ Programming Languages:
  - $\rightarrow$  Python (10+ years of experience)
  - $\rightarrow$  Bash (10+ years of experience)
  - → HTML, CSS & JavaScript (level: intermediate-advanced)
  - $\rightarrow$  C/C++, PHP, Ruby & Perl (level: basic)
  - $\rightarrow$  Erlang & Elixir (learning now)
- ♦ Tools (software):
  - → Git & GitHub, Mercurial (version control, software repository)
  - → Django, web2py & flask (Python Web frameworks)
  - → Jira (project management)
  - → markdown & LATEX (markup language, high-quality document preparation system)
  - $\rightarrow$  Arduino
  - $\rightarrow$  Debian GNU/Linux
- $\diamond$  Methodologies & Other Skills:
  - → Scrum and eXtreme Programming
  - $\rightarrow$  Test-driven development
  - → Development and access to REST APIs, Web crawling and parsing
  - → GNU/Linux systems administration
  - $\rightarrow$  Screencasts
  - $\rightarrow$  Remote working
  - $\rightarrow$  Conferences organization

### Remarkable Achievements

- ♦ PythonQuito Organizer (Charlas Pythónicas and Django Girls) Quito, March 2016.
- ♦ Open data initiatives such as brasil.io and the rows Python library.
- ♦ Remodeling and development of new versions the PyPLN project: distributed natural language processing (free software) – from 2013 to 2014.
- ♦ PythonBrasil[8] Organizer, the biggest Python conference in Latin America (approx. 450 attendees from all over the world, 4 days of duration) Rio de Janeiro, November 2012.
- ♦ Brazilian reference on Arduino, for a huge number of talks and courses on the topic.
- ♦ Foundation and coordination of the ArduInRio user group Rio de Janeiro, June 2010.
- ♦ Foundation and coordination of the Coding Dojo de Niterói group Niterói, October 2009.
- SeTel (Telecommunications Week) Organizer, Fluminense Federal University (approx. 180 attendees) Niterói, October 2007.

### **Academic Education**

- ♦ Incomplete graduation in Telecommunications Engeneering at Fluminense Federal University from 2005 to 2010.
- ♦ High School: Colégio Ruy Barbosa, Três Rios/RJ.
- ♦ Elementary School: Escola Nossa Senhora de Fátima, Três Rios/RJ.

### Academic Highlights – Fluminense Federal University

- Scholarship on Scientific Research on ReMoTE project (Network Monitoring for Power Transmission Lines), MídiaCom Laboratory from December 2008 to January 2010.
- Scholarship on Scientific Reserach on Complex Systems and Statistical Physics Group (many projects), Physics Institute, guided by Professor Thadeu Penna — from April 2007 to November 2008.
- ♦ Volunteer Math Teacher, Pre-College Preparatory Course, Engineering School from March 2007 to December 2007.
- Scholarship on Tutorial Education Program on Telecommunications (PET-Tele), acting on tasks related to research, teaching and university extension to enhance the Telecommunications Engineering course, guided by Professor Alexandre de la Vega — from September 2006 to March 2008.
- $\diamond$  Volunteer as beta-tester on the pilot project of University Mesh Networks, MídiaCom Laboratory (GT-Mesh/RNP) 2006.
- ♦ GNU/Linux systems administrator and Physics experiments guide at Casa da Descoberta (Science Dissemination Center) July 2005 to September 2006.